Finding Aid for William S. Housel papers, 1916-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William S. Housel papers 1916-1968
Housel, William S., 1901-
85216 Aa 2
Professor of civil engineering and specialist in soil mechanics at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, daily logs of activities, class materials, conference and lecture files, and professional reports and soil investigation studies; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
5 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
The collection was the gift of Henry W. Wallace (donor no. 6258 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William S. Housel, a recognized authority in the field of soil mechanics, was born February 16, 1901 in Boulder, Colorado. He graduated from the University of Michigan with B.S. and M.S. degrees in Civil Engineering in 1923 and 1931 respectively. He was appointed instructor at the University in 1924, assistant professor in 1929, associate professor in 1936, and full professor in 1950. While at the University, Housel established the Soil Mechanics Laboratory which was used in the teaching of subsurface construction problems.
Besides teaching, Housel was a prolific writer, and a consultant on numerous engineering projects. In 1933, he was appointed director of the State Highway Laboratory, which was operated jointly by the University and the Michigan State Highway Department. And in 1934, he was appointed research consultant for the Highway Department, a position he held throughout his working life. In addition, Housel worked on hundreds of civil engineering projects here and abroad, and was a consultant for the Mackinac Bridge project, the Detroit Civic Center, and the metropolitan Detroit expressway system. In 1960, Housel was visiting lecturer at the University of Chile, and in 1965, he was visiting professor at the University of Hawaii. Housel died in 1978.
The Housel papers include correspondence, newspaper clippings, lectures, conference materials, class materials, and various reports and studies of soil investigations. Of interest is a series of daily logs kept by Housel in the period 1962-1968 and which concern some of his consulting projects.
Subjects:
Engineering.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Housel, William Stuart, 1901-; Soil mechanics.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Civil Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Housel, William Stuart, 1901-; University of Michigan. College of Engineering. Class of 1923.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--Anniversaries, etc.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.); University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; Camp Davis (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Boxing.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal Papers
  - Biographical Sketch (Box 1)
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
  - Awards and Citations (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1931-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with former students 1946-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with, and thesis of, Professor Pao Cheng King 1941 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - Correspondence (arranged alphabetically)
    - Flanakin, H.A. (Box 1)
    - McLaughlin, W.W. (Box 1)
    - Palmer, L.A. (Box 1)
  - Daily Logs
    - 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - AEC news clippings 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - News clippings (Willow Run Airport) (Box 1)
  - News clippings 1967 (Box 1)
- Professional Papers
  - Class Materials
    - 1941
      - Engineering Defense Training (Box 1)
    - 1942
      - Soil Mechanics in Advance (Box 1)
      - Base Construction (Box 1)
    - 1965
      - University of Hawaii (Box 1)
      - Memoranda (Civil Engineering Department) (Box 1)
      - Lecture Notes (Soils and Foundation Engineering) (Box 1)
      - Class Notes (Box 1)
    - Undated
      - Lecture (Soil Resistance) (Box 1)
    - 1962-1963
      - Seminar Materials (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan, Department of Civil Engineering
    - 1936, Report on Civil Engineering Department (Box 2)
    - 1960-1961, Staff meetings and memos (Box 2)
    - 1966, Miscellaneous memos on various meetings (Box 2)
  - Conferences, Lectures, and Symposiums
    - 1954
      - Lecture on soil mechanics (University of Minnesota) (Box 2)
    - 1959
      - Cleveland Engineering Society (Box 2)
        (includes paper on soil mechanics)
    - 1967
      - Miscellaneous information (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - Soil Mechanics Bibliography (Box 2)
    - 1937
      - Principles of Soil Stabilization (Box 2)
    - 1942
      - Measurement of Cohesive Soil Properties (Box 2)
    - 1955
      - Design Memorandums (Box 2)
    - 1955
      - Vertical Sand Drains (Box 2)
    - 1960
      - Applied Soil Mechanics (textbook) (Box 2)
    - Undated
      - Bearing Capacity of Soil (outline) (Box 2)
  - Reports and Soil Investigations
    - 1919-1960
      - State Highway Laboratory, original test reports (Bibliography) (Box 2)
    - 1925-1967
      - Complete File of All Projects since 1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926
      - Calcium Admixture Investigation (Herbert Weil) (Box 2)
    - 1929
      - The Effect of Non-Durable Particles on the Life and Strength of Concrete (Box 2)
    - 1929
      - The removal of Ice From Concrete (Box 2)
    - 1932
      - Investigation of Durako (Box 2)
    - 1932
      - The Use of Calcium Chlorine and Sodium Chlorine in the Treatment of Icy Pavements (Box 2)
    - 1936
      - Burton Tower (cement and concrete lab tests) (Box 3)
    - 1942
      - Southfield Freeway (Monroe Blvd. crossing) (Box 3)
    - 1945
      - Michigan Ave., Lansing (Box 3)
    - 1946
      - Michigan State College, Natural Science Bldg. (Box 3)
    - 1947
      - Cheboygan soil-cement project (Box 3)
    - 1947
      - Lansing Civic Auditorium (Box 3)
    - 1947
      - Michigan State College Stadium (Box 3)
    - 1948
      - Lansing City Hall Foundation Investigation (Box 3)
    - 1948
      - Michigan State College (Box 3)
    - 1948
      - New Y.M.C.A. Bldg., Lansing (Box 3)
    - 1949
      - State Journal Bldg., Lansing (Box 3)
    - 1950
      - Michigan State College Chapel (Box 3)
    - 1951
      - Michigan State College Library (Box 3)
    - 1952
      - Ludington Junior High School (Box 3)
    - 1952
      - Michigan State College Women's Dormitory (Box 3)
    - 1953
      - Wire Reinforcement Institute Projects (Box 3)
    - 1966
      - AEC Accelerator Site (Northfield Twp.) (Box 3)
- Other materials
  - Miscellaneous Reprints, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Topical Files
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Raw Water Booster Station Detroit, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Youngstown, Ohio 1966, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Films circa 1938-1950s (Box 5)
    (partial inventory included)
  - Stenorette Sound tapes, 3 tapes (Box 5)
  - Photographs: reunion photograph of University of Michigan Engineering Class of 1923 (Box 5)
  - Minutes of Delta Club (high school) 1915-1916 (Box 5)
  - Notebook (Tinian-Saipan) 1944 (Box 5)
  - Loose items from scrapbook (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1914-1925 (Volume 1)
    (Contains photographs, clippings, and memorabilia relating to Ann Arbor High School activities and to his years as a student at the University of Michigan)